Finding Aid for Douglas MacArthur collection
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
Douglas MacArthur collection 1885-1983 1917-1919
MacArthur, Douglas collection
Diedrich, D. N. (Duane Norman)
885 items
wclmss001314
The Douglas MacArthur collection is made up of military documents related to General Douglas MacArthur and the 42nd (Rainbow) Division during the first World War, and miscellaneous letters, documents, photographs, published works, and one diary illuminating various aspects of the General's public career and personal life.
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
Donated by D. N. Diedrich, 1987-2013. M-2370 et al.
The collection is open to research.
Biography
Douglas MacArthur
Douglas MacArthur was born on January 26, 1880, the youngest child of (Capt.) Arthur MacArthur (1845-1912) and Mary Pinkney Hardy (1852-1935). His siblings were Arthur (1876-1923), and Malcolm (1878-1883), who died before his seventh birthday.
Douglas MacArthur graduated from West Texas Military Academy in 1897 as valedictorian and two years later entered West Point. In 1903 he graduated as First Captain, West Point's highest honor. In September 1903, he joined the 3rd Battalion Engineers in San Francisco, and almost immediately was sent to Manila, Philippines. The next year he was promoted to First Lieutenant, and in 1906 returned to the United States. After being made Captain of Engineers at Leavenworth in 1911, MacArthur was assigned to Vera Cruz to report information to the War Department. While serving as military aide to the Secretary of War in 1916, he conceived the idea of expanding the existing National Guard through volunteer enlistment and turned into combat divisions - an idea that would be used for the formation of the 42nd Division.
In 1917, MacArthur was appointed Colonel and Chief of Staff of the 42nd (Rainbow) Division. As Commander of the 84th Infantry Brigade, he led his troops during the vitally important Argonne Campaign in the last months of the war. In 1919, the 42nd Division returned to the United States, and MacArthur accepted an appointment as Superintendent of West Point. While there, he became permanent Brigadier General. MacArthur married Louise Cromwell Brooks in 1922, the year he was posted to command the Philippine Division, but they divorced seven years later. In November 1929, MacArthur was promoted to General and chosen as the man to replace General Summerall as the Chief of Staff, U.S. Army. In 1937, MacArthur married a second time - to Jean Marie Faircloth, and they had a son, Arthur, a year later.
In December 1941, the Japanese Army attacked and defeated MacArthur's Philippine Army on the Bataan Peninsula. The following March, MacArthur was ordered from the Philippines to command the Allied troops with Thomas Blamey. For six months, MacArthur concentrated on the defense of New Guinea, which led to an ambitious counter-attack in January and February 1943. On the day the Japanese surrendered, MacArthur was appointed Supreme Commander of Allied Powers.
MacArthur remained in occupied Japan until 1950, orchestrating the reformation of the post-war country. On the 29th of June, 1950, MacArthur went to South Korea with American forces to assess the situation after North Korea's invasion of South Korea. This assessment led to Truman's commitment of U.S. troops to a ground war in Korea. The North Koreans abandoned Seoul on September 28, 1950, after MacArthur's successful military plan to attack through Inchon. As a result of the success of this campaign, China decided to enter the Korean War. MacArthur was ordered by the Joint Chiefs of Staff and the Secretary of Defense, in conjunction with a U.N. resolution, to proceed north of the 38th parallel. Chinese troops attacked, leading to the withdrawal of MacArthur's troops back south of the 38th. By this time, MacArthur had disobeyed the military order to employ only Korean forces in the frontier provinces. On the 24th of March, MacArthur issued a lengthy communiqué complaining about the restrictions on his forces and taunted the enemy for their lack of industrial power and inability to maintain even moderate air and naval power. This pronouncement and his previous insubordination caused President Truman to relieve MacArthur of his command.
In April 1951, General Douglas MacArthur returned to San Francisco to thousands of cheering citizens. On April 19 he presented his case regarding his relief of command to a joint session of congress. During his remaining years, MacArthur traveled throughout the United States to make speeches, in which he often denounced communists and socialists, and spoke of corrupt administration and heavy taxation. At the age of 84, on April 5, 1964, Douglas MacArthur died in a hospital in Washington.
The 42nd (Rainbow) Division
The Rainbow Division was created in 1917 as a composite division of members of the Regular Army and the National Guard solely for use in the war in Europe. The 42nd arrived in Europe in 1917 as the war was entering a new phase: Russia had dropped out of the war, America was joining the war, and Germany was racing to provide tremendous reinforcement before the American forces arrived.
In February 1918 the 42nd Division, part of the First U.S. Army Corps, was ordered to the Luneville area for a month of training with French units from the 7th French Army Corps. While there, the Rainbow Division distinguished itself as "a first class combat Division."
The first assignment for the 42nd was to relieve the 128th French Infantry Division from the Baccarat Sector. In the war, this was the first time an American Division held a Sector on its own. The Division successfully held the Baccarat Sector until relief orders were sent on June 16, 1918. Two weeks later, the 42nd Division went to the front at the Battle of Champagne alongside the 21st French Army Corps. After an attack by the Germans on the fifteenth of July, the 42nd assisted in the Champagne defense until the end of the battle (July 18). The Sixth French Army Corps was given the Rainbow Division to pursue the supposedly retreating enemy at the Battle of the Ourcq from July 25-July 27, 1918. From July 28-August 1st, the Allies captured strongpoints of the German position. August 2-August 3rd, the 42nd Division assisted in pursuing the enemy until relieved by the 4th Regular Division.
After the Battle of the Ourcq, Douglas MacArthur was given command of the 84th Infantry Brigade (William Hughes, Jr., replaced him as Chief of Staff, 42nd Division). In September, the Rainbow Division, then under the 4th American Army Corps, was ordered to attack the center of the south side of the San Mihiel Salient and was assigned to the defense of the Essey-Pannes Sector until September 30, when it was relieved by the 89th Division.
On October 11-12, 1918, the Rainbow Division relieved the 1st Division on the Verdun front. In order to break the 2nd German line of defense, the hill called The Cote de Chatillon had to be taken. From October 13-16, Brigadier General Douglas MacArthur commanded the 84th Infantry Division to the successful capture of Hill 288 (a strongly fortified point on the Kreimhilde Stellung), the Tuilerie Ferme, and the Cote de Chatillon (beyond the enemy's strong line of resistance).
The next attack took place November 1, 1918. The 42nd Division provided machine gun fire for the advancement of the 2nd and 89th Divisions. After this victory, and as a result of divisional rivalry (and a difference in opinion as to the exact nature of a memorandum), the 42nd and the 1st Divisions (of the First American Army Corps and the 5th American Army Corps respectively) 'raced' for the glory of partaking in the (potential) final engagement of the war, in Sedan. On November 6-7, the Rainbow, the 4th French Army, and the 1st and 77th American Divisions, fought south of the Meuse (south of Sedan). The fighting ended when the enemy requested an armistice on November 9, 1918. The 42nd Division backed off and was able to claim that the Americans who got closest to Sedan were members of the 166th Infantry of the 83rd Infantry Brigade. The armistice was signed two days later.
The 42nd Division remained in France and occupied Germany until May 1, 1919, when the last unit arrived home. Less than two weeks later, the last Brigade was demobilized.
The Douglas MacArthur collection has been organized into four series. Within these series, the papers are separated into distinct sub-series groups.
Series I: Correspondence and diaries
Sub-series I: Letters and diary to Florence Adams (Box 1)
Sub-series II: Letters from Douglas MacArthur to Louise Cromwell (Brooks) MacArthur (Box 1)
Sub-series III: Letters from Douglas MacArthur to Hamilton Fish, Jr. (Box 1)
Sub-series IV: Miscellaneous letters and documents pertaining to Douglas MacArthur (Box 1)
Series II: Papers related to the 42nd (Rainbow) Division
Sub-series I: Military documents to the 42nd Division from external military units (Boxes 1-2)
Sub-series II: Military documents from the 42nd Division to various military units (Boxes 2-4)
Sub-series III: Internal military documents from and to various military units in the 42nd Division. (Box 5)
Sub-series IV: Kenneth A. Sutherland Notebook. (Box 6)
Series III: Photographs and miscellaneous papers pertaining to Douglas MacArthur
Sub-series I: Aerial photographs and negatives, 91st Reconnaissance Squadron. (Box 7)
Sub-series II: Miscellaneous photographs and papers. (Box 8)
Series IV: Published works.
The MacArthur collection contains 885 letters, documents, photographs, and published works dating from March 23, 1885, to July 5, 1983. The bulk of the material (710 items) consists of military documents and manuscript notes from September 8, 1917 to January 27, 1919.
The military materials include general orders, field orders, field messages, memoranda, intelligence, and communications, related to the U.S. 42nd Division (The Rainbow Division), A.E.F., founded in 1917. The majority of the collection falls during the period of time from late 1917 to early August 1918, when Douglas MacArthur was Chief of Staff for the 42nd Division. Documents from military units that fought alongside the 42nd Division (both French and American), the U.S. Chemical Warfare, and the Intelligence Divisions -- as well as various German, French, and American communications -- are included. Organizational documents, such as training schedules, and march tables, are also present. A considerable number, if not all, of these materials must have been approved or viewed by MacArthur, and many of the items in this collection bear his initials or the initials of his information assistant, William Hughes, Jr. From early August 1918 until the armistice was signed on November 11, 1918, MacArthur acted as the commanding officer for the 84th Infantry Brigade, and several military orders bear his name.
Seventy-six letters in the collection (located in Box 1) are either from Douglas MacArthur or pertain in some way to him. Six of these items, dated 1904, pertain to MacArthur and Florence Adams, whom he met in the Philippines, including a 46-page diary MacArthur wrote to Adams while he was on board a ship from Manila to the United States. Five letters, dated 1921 and 1925, are written by MacArthur to Louise Brooks who became Mrs. Douglas MacArthur in 1922. These letters contain both romantic content as well as personal reflections on the events in MacArthur's life at the time. Also included are nine letters from MacArthur to Hamilton Fish, Jr., dated 1921-1934. The remainder of the correspondence is a miscellaneous collection of letters written by Douglas MacArthur, Jean MacArthur, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Harry S. Truman, and others.
The Douglas MacArthur collection also contains a notebook kept by Kenneth A. Sutherland, veteran of the 42nd Division, which contains a selection of items related to the Division's post-war activities and reunions; 40 aerial photographs and negatives taken by the 91st Reconnaissance Squadron, October 10, 1918; several photographs of Douglas MacArthur; thirteen published works by or about the General; and other miscellaneous materials.
Subjects:
Aisne, Battle of the, France, 1918.; Argonne, Battle of the, 1918.; Brooks, Louise Cromwell.; Chateau-Thierry, Battle of, 1918.; Chemical Warfare.; Chemical Warfare--Safety Measures.; Chemical Weapons.; Communications, Military.; Fish, Hamilton, 1849-1936.; Gases, Asphyxiating and Poisonous--War Use.; Marne, 2nd Battle of the, France, 1918.; Military Assistance, French.; Military Intelligence.; Military Reconnaissance.; Saint-Mihiel (France), Battle of, 1918.; Signals and Signaling.; United States. Army.; United States. Army--Artillery.; United States. Army--Artillery--Drill and Tactics.; United States. Army--Communication Systems.; United States. Army--Drill and Tactics.; United States. Army--Equipment.; United States. Army--Field Service.; United States. Army--History.; United States. Army--Information Services.; United States. Army--Medals, Badges, Decorations, etc.; United States. Army--Organization.; United States. Army--Records and Correspondence.; United States. Army--Safety Measures.; United States. Army--Sanitary Affairs.; United States. Army. Infantry Division, 42nd.; United States--History--1913-1921.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Aerial Operations.; World War, 1914-1918--Campaigns-France.
Contributors:
Adams, Florence.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Granara, J. Ralph.; Hughes, William.; Hunt, Haroldson L.; Kean, Robert Winthrop.; Luhrs, H. Ernst.; MacArthur, Arthur, 1845-1912.; MacArthur, Douglas, 1880-1964.; MacArthur, Jean Faircloth.; Mark, Clark.; Menoher, Charles Thomas, 1862-1930; Rhodes, Weldon E.; Sutherland, Kenneth A.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; United States. Army. Infantry Division, 42nd.
Genre Terms:
Books.; Diaries.; Diaries.; Letters (correspondence); Newspapers.; Orders (military records); Photographs.
- Correspondence and Diaries (Box 1)
  - Letters and diary to Florence Adams.
    6 items pertaining to Florence Adams including a lengthy diary written by Douglas MacArthur on his return trip from the Philippines in 1904.
    - 1904 October 15. Printed Receipt to Lt. D. MacArthur, with ANS by MacArthur on back.
    - 1904 October. Douglas MacArthur ALS to Florence Adams.
    - 1904 October. Douglas MacArthur ALS to Florence Adams.
    - 1904 September-1904 October 16. Florence Adams account of days spent with MacArthur., 4 pp.
    - 1904 October 17-1904 November 25. Douglas MacArthur diary written for Florence Adams., 46pp.
    - Undated [1905 January?]. Douglas MacArthur ALS to Florence Adams.
  - Letters from Douglas MacArthur to Louise Cromwell (Brooks) MacArthur.
    5 letters from Douglas MacArthur to Louise Cromwell Brooks (later Mrs. Louise MacArthur) including romantic letters and a reflection on his father after visiting Kenesaw Mountain where he fought during the Civil War.
    - 1921 October 15 (post). Douglas MacArthur ALS to Louise C. Brooks.
    - 1921 October 23 (post). Douglas MacArthur ALS to Louise C. Brooks.
    - 1921 November 18 (post). Douglas MacArthur ALS to Louise C. Brooks post.
    - 1925 May 28 (post). Douglas MacArthur ALS to Mrs. Louise MacArthur post.
    - 1925 May 30 (post). Douglas MacArthur ALS to Mrs. Louise MacArthur post.
  - Letters from Douglas MacArthur to Hamilton Fish, Jr.
    9 Letters from Douglas MacArthur to Hamilton Fish Jr. during the period of time when MacArthur was Superintendent of West Point, and Chief of Staff, U.S. Army.
    - 1921 June 28. Douglas MacArthur TLS to Hamilton Fish, Jr.
    - 1921 December 2. Douglas MacArthurTLS to Hamilton Fish, Jr.
    - 1931 June 9. Douglas MacArthur TLS to Hamilton Fish, Jr.
    - 1931 June 30. Douglas MacArthur TLS to Hamilton Fish, Jr.
    - 1932 August 24. Douglas MacArthur TLS to Hamilton Fish, Jr.
    - 1932 August 25. Douglas MacArthur TLS to Hamilton Fish, Jr.
    - 1933 January 6. Douglas MacArthur TLS to Hamilton Fish, Jr.
    - 1933 June 29. Douglas MacArthur TLS to Hamilton Fish, Jr.
    - 1934 February 1. Douglas MacArthur TLS to Hamilton Fish, Jr.
  - Miscellaneous letters and documents by or pertaining to Douglas MacArthur.
    - 1885 March 23. Arthur MacArthur ALS to Mrs. Talmage.
    - 1893 July 7. Arthur MacArthur TLS to W.G. Purdy.
    - 1893 July 27. Arthur MacArthur TLS to Thomas S. Wright.
    - 1898 February 5. Douglas MacArthur ALS to Frances [S. Rockwell]; Milwaukee, Wis[consin].
      This letter is accompanied by an 8x10" photograph of the General, inscribed and signed "To Francis [sic.] With life-long friendship. Douglas MacArthur Tokyo 1949."
    - 1898 February 28. Douglas MacArthur to Frances S. Rockwell; Milwaukee, [Wisconsin].
    - 1902 July 31. Arthur MacArthur TLS to Allen H. Wright.
    - 1909 June 16. Arthur MacArthur ALS to Mr. Varney.
    - 1909 June 17. [G.] Middlebrook TLS to Arthur MacArthur.
    - [1913] March 28. Douglas MacArthur ALS to H.S. Rooksby.
    - 1918 August 13. Charles Menoher document, to 42nd Division.
    - 1920 December 6. Douglas MacArthur TLS to Marion Leroy Burton.
    - 1920 December 14. Asst. of Marion Burton TLS (copy) to Douglas MacArthur.
    - 1921 March 19. Douglas MacArthur TLS to W.L. Calver.
    - 1921 April 30. Douglas MacArthur TLS to Wilt Robinson.
    - 1927 October 28. Douglas MacArthur TLS to Murray Hulbert.
    - 1930 November 25. Douglas MacArthur TLS to Wm. A. Wolf; Washington, D.C.
    - 1931 February 14. Douglas MacArthur TLS to Dr. S.C.G. Watkins.
    - 1931 August 12. Douglas MacArthur TLS to Gen. Cornelius Vanderbilt.
    - 1932 February 22. Douglas MacArthur typed document, General Orders No. 3.
    - 1932 February 22. Douglas MacArthur typed document, Circular No. 6.
    - 1933 May 1. Douglas MacArthur TLS to Basil O'Connor.
    - 1933 September 8. Douglas MacArthur TLS to Ernest Lundeen.
    - 1936 February 4. Douglas MacArthur TLS to Capt. Harold D. Kehm.
    - 1942 December 22. Douglas MacArthur postal telegraph to "the men and women of LC Smith & Corona Typewriters Inc."
    - [1944] April 20. Dwight Eisenhower ALS to Mamie Eisenhower.
    - 1945 October 14. Douglas MacArthur TLS to Mrs. Lena L. Smith.
    - 1947 May 2 (transmitted). Douglas MacArthur telegram draft.
    - 1947 July 16. Douglas MacArthur TLS to Colonel Walter Wolf; Tokyo, Japan.
    - 1948 August 11. Douglas MacArthur TLS to George W. DeWitt; Tokyo, Japan.
    - 1948 December 6. Douglas MacArthur TLS to George J. Schoeneman.
    - 1950 August 16. Harry S. Truman TLS to Douglas MacArthur.
    - 1950 September 24. Jean MacArthur ALS to Dr. Poling.
    - 1950 September 24. Douglas MacArthur DS, to William R. Landin. Membership certificate in MacArthur's Honor Guard.
      located in Oversize manuscripts
    - [1951 April 4]. Douglas MacArthur ANS to [Laurence E.] Bunker.
    - 1951 April 18. Harry S. Truman TLS to Cornelius Vanderbilt, Jr.
    - 1951 April 18. Harry S. Truman TLS to Cyrus S. Ching.
    - 1951 April 20. Robert W[inthrop] Kean TLS to Stephen Siteman.
    - 1951 May 15. Ike [Dwight D.] Eisenhower TLS to Douglas MacArthur.
    - 1951 July 2. H. Ernst Luhrs TLS (with an additional copy) to Douglas MacArthur.
    - 1952 June 18. H[aroldson] L. Hunt TLS to Francis Case.
    - 1952 July 10. Harry S. Truman TLS to Russ Stewart.
    - 1953 January 22. Douglas MacArthur TLS to Bascom N. Timmons.
    - 1953 July 16. Jean MacArthur TLS to Mrs. Goodwin.
    - 1953 August 8. Jean MacArthur TLS to Mrs. Goodwin; enclosing one family photograph.
    - [1953] September 5. Arthur MacArthur ALS to Mrs. Goodwin.
    - 1955 July 31. J. Ralph Granara ALS to Douglas MacArthur; enclosing: MacArthur, Douglas MacArthur ALS to J. Ralph Granera, [1955].
    - 1956 January 26. Douglas MacArthur TLS to Brig. Gen. L.A. Diller.
    - 1956 February 20. Douglas MacArthur TLS to John Marquez.
    - 1957 August 5. Harry S. Truman TLS to John Norman.
    - 1958 July 2. Douglas MacArthur TLS to Marshall Lachner.
    - 1961 April 14. Douglas MacArthur ALS to John J. McSweeney.
    - 1962 July 31. Printed Document Signed: Sperry Rand Corporation, Annual Meeting of Stockholders.
    - 1966 January 5. Dwight Eisenhower TLS to Edgar Garbisch.
    - 1969 September 26. Jean MacArthur TLS to "Ed."
    - 1983 April 29. Weldon E. Rhodes ALS to Frank.
    - 1983 July 5. Clark Mark TLS to Joseph Fawls.
    - [ ] March, 21. Douglas MacArthur ALS to General Bundy.
- Papers pertaining to the 42nd (Rainbow) Division
  - Military documents to the 42nd Division from external military units.
    137 documents and memos directed to units of the 42nd Division from various military units within and outside the 42nd Division. Arranged by unit.
    - General Headquarters, A.E.F., 1918 April 8., 1 Document
    - Headquarters IV Army Corps, A.E.F., 1918 August 20-1918 September 26., 10 Documents
    - Headquarters V Army Corps, 1918 October 9-1918 October 31., 17 Documents
    - P.C. 64th Brigade, 1918 October 12-1918 October 13., 3 Documents
    - U.S. Army 89th Division, 1918 September 9-1918 September 30., 3 TD Cys
    - French 4th Army Corps, 1918 June 26., 4 Documents (Box 2)
    - French 5th Army Corps, 1918 May 30-1918 July 2., 44 Documents
    - French 6th Army Corps, 1918 June 1-1918 August 8., 10 Documents
    - French 7th Army Corps, 1918 April 9-1918 April 22., 3 Documents
    - Miscellaneous French Documents, 1918 June 26-1918 September 24., 8 Documents
    - German Communique, 1918 August 7-1918 October 31., 7 Documents
    - French Communique, 1918 August 10-1918 October 31., 12 Documents
    - American Communique, 1918 October 28-1918 October 31., 6 Documents
    - Chemical Warfare Service, 1918 August 14-1918 October 16., 9 Documents
  - Military documents from the 42nd Division to various military units.
    293 military documents from the 42nd Division, A.E.F., Chiefs of Staff and General Staff Douglas MacArthur, William Hughes, Jr., R.H. Williams, Craig Malin, and H.A. Drum to various military units, September 8, 1917-January 27, 1919.
    - Headquarters 42nd Division [Douglas MacArthur]., 53 Documents
    - Headquarters 42nd Division [William Hughes, Jr.]., 12 Documents (Box 3)
    - Headquarters 42nd Division [R.H. Williams]., 6 Documents
    - Headquarters 42nd Division [Craig Malin]., 5 Documents
    - Headquarters 42nd Division [H.A. Drum]., 1 Document
    - Headquarters 42nd Division [William Hughes, Jr.]., 73 Documents
    - Headquarters 42nd Division [Douglas MacArthur]., 2 Documents
    - Headquarters 42nd Division [R.H. Williams]., 1 Document
    - Headquarters 42nd Division [Hughes, William, Jr.] 1919 September 14-1919 January 27., 120 Documents (Box 4)
  - Internal military documents from and to various military units in the 42nd Division. (Box 5)
    280 internal documents and memos from and to various military units in the 42nd Division, A.E.F., November 18, 1917-April 1, 1919. Arranged by unit.
    - Headquarters 42nd Division, 1917 November 18-1918 November 28., 35 Documents
    - Miscellaneous Documents 42nd Division, 1917 November 24-1918 March 25., 6 Documents
    - Miscellaneous Documents 42nd Division, 1918 May 23-1918 October 28., 16 Documents
    - Miscellaneous Documents 42nd Division, Undated., 33 Documents
    - Miscellaneous Annexes and Appendices, Undated., 13 Documents
    - Headquarters 67th Field Artillery Brigade, 1918 March 24-1918 September 25., 11 Documents
    - Headquarters 83rd Infantry Brigade, 1918 March 31-1918 October 18., 33 Documents
    - Headquarters 84th Infantry Brigade, 1918 March 31-1919 April 1., 86 Documents
    - Headquarters 167th Infantry, 1918 April 2-1918 October 19., 22 Documents
    - Headquarters 168th Infantry, 1918 April 7-1918 October 21., 24 Documents
  - Kenneth A. Sutherland Notebook. (Box 6)